Greetings!
We’re so happy you could join us.
皆さん ようこそ!
ご一緒できることを
嬉しく思います
It’s a new service year
and a new monthly program.
新たな奉仕年度 そして
新たなマンスリープログラムです
共に司会をするのは
セス・ハイアット兄弟です
And look, we have a new cohost,
Brother Seth Hyatt,
affectionately known as Rocky.
ロッキーとも呼ばれていますね
ロッキー
どんなプログラムを楽しめますか？
Now, Rocky, what can the friends
have to look forward to?
You can look forward
to this dramatization
宣教奉仕における喜びを
失いそうになっている—
where we meet a sister who is
一人の姉妹のドラマがあります
on the brink of losing
her joy in the ministry.
何が必要でしたか？
What does she need to do?
非常に実際的な内容から
益を得られます
We will all benefit
from the very practical application.
And we’re also going to see
an amazing video
さらに 世界本部のアート部門に関する
素晴らしいビデオもあります
from the Art Department
at world headquarters.
What do they do?
And how do we benefit from their work?
何が行われていますか？
益を得るために何ができますか？
This segment is going
to answer those questions.
その答えが得られます
In some countries in Europe,
congregations are involved
ヨーロッパではトラックの駐車場で
証言がなされています
in witnessing at truck stops.
This has proved to be a very productive way
of reaching individuals
これは 家から離れて暮らす
人々に達する点で—
who spend most of their time
away from home.
非常に産出的な奉仕といえます
So if you’re a first-time viewer, welcome.
初めてご覧の皆さんも
いつもご覧の皆さんもようこそ！
If you’re a regular viewer, welcome back.
9月の JW Broadcastingです!
This is the September program
of JW Broadcasting!
Have you enjoyed studying the book
皆さんは「信仰に倣う」の本の
研究を楽しんでおられますか？
Imitate Their Faith as much as I have?
It’s a wonderful book,
isn’t it?
素晴らしい本ですね
And I was particularly captivated
by the introduction.
特に 序章に心を
引き付けられます
There was a point in the introduction
そこでは 想像力を働かせるよう
励まされています
that encouraged us
to use our imagination
when we’re reading the Bible:
to see the sights,
to hear the sounds,
どんな光景が見え
どんな音が聞こえ—
to smell the aromas,
to try to capture the feelings
どんな匂いがするか想像し
登場人物の気持ちを感じ取るのです
of the individuals
that we are reading about.
Now, of course, we don’t want
our imagination to run away with us,
もちろん 考えすぎるのは
良くありませんが—
but at the same time,
we do want to get
読んでいることをしっかりと
思い描くのは大切なことです
a solid mental picture
of what we’re reading.
今日は そのことについて
お話したいと思います
And that’s what I’d like
to talk to you about today.
When you’re reading the Bible,
try to get the whole picture.
聖書を読む際には
全体像をつかみましょう
Now we’ll use a couple
of well-known Bible accounts to illustrate.
例として よく知られた聖書の記述を
取り上げてみましょう
Have you been raised
in a stepfamily or a blended family?
ステップファミリーの中で
育った経験がありますか？
If you have,
did you know that you have
そうであれば ヤコブの子である
ヨセフと共通点があるでしょう
something in common with Joseph,
the son of Jacob?
Joseph was raised
with ten half brothers
ヨセフは 10人の異母兄弟を含む
大きな家族で育ちました
in a large blended family.
So now you want to try to view
これを 一つの集合体として
とらえてみましょう
this family as a composite.
You want to try to figure out
how did people mesh
お互いにどのような影響を
及ぼしたのかを考えます
or how did they clash
within this family.
家族の一人一人について—
What would you do?
Well, you might start by writing down
some of the characteristics
その特徴などを書き出すところからー
始めることができるでしょう
of the individual members
of the family.
ヨセフや 彼の異母兄弟に
ついてはどうですか？
What about Joseph’s half brothers
and Joseph himself?
What do you know about them?
どんなことを知っていますか？
What about Judah,
Simeon, Levi,
ユダ シメオン レビ ダン ナフタリに
ついて考えてみてください
Dan, Naphtali
—what do you know?
So write down
their characteristics,
彼らの特徴などを書き出し
お互いの関係について考えます
and try to figure out
how they might get along.
Sometimes there is
one individual incident
聖書に記録されている出来事を
読むときには—
that’s recorded in the Bible,
but we mustn’t forget:
ある人の行動はー
他の人にも影響を与えるということを—
People’s actions
have a way of affecting other people.
忘れないようにしましょう
So when you read
about a certain incident in the Bible,
それで何かの出来事を読むときには—
try to imagine who
might have been affected by that incident.
影響を受けた人についても考えましょう
Take an example.
例を挙げましょう
In the book of Genesis,
we read that Jacob’s son Reuben
創世記には ヤコブの息子ルベンが—
ビルハと性的な不道徳を犯したことがー
committed sexual immorality
with Bilhah.
記録されています
Well, that had an effect
on other people without doubt.
周囲の人々にも影響が
及んだことでしょう
Who was Reuben?
ルベンはどんな人でしたか？
He was Leah’s oldest son.
レアが最初に生んだ子です
Who was Bilhah?
ではビルハとは誰ですか？
Rachel’s handmaiden.
ラケルの侍女です
Do you think that there might have been
a little animosity or tension
レアとラケルの結婚生活の
始まりについて考えると—
between Leah and Rachel sometimes,
二人の間には 幾らかの対立や緊張が
あったとは考えられませんか？
especially when you consider
how their marriages started out?
きっと そうだったでしょう
There may have been.
さらに 母親の態度は
その息子たちの態度にも—
And it may be
that the attitudes of the women
had some bearing on the attitudes
of their sons as well.
何らかの影響を与えるものです
So you take all of these things
into consideration.
こうしたことすべてを
考慮に入れましょう
Now, Bilhah had two sons,
Dan and Naphtali.
ビルハには二人の息子がいました
ダンとナフタリです
How do you think
they felt when they learned
では 年長の異母兄弟が
自分の母親と淫行を犯したと聞いて—
that their oldest brother,
or half brother,
had committed fornication
with their mother?
どう感じたでしょうか？
So there could have been
tension there.
緊張が走ったに違いありません
And this all goes into the mix
ひとつの集合体として家族をとらえると
こうしたことがわかってきます
when we’re considering
the family as a composite.
さて ヨセフが17歳のときー
Now, do you picture
Joseph at age 17
10人の異母兄弟は
幾つくらいでしたか？
with ten much older half brothers,
maybe in their 30’s,
30歳ぐらいでー
some old enough to be his father?
彼の父親にもなれるくらいでしょうか？
Not true.
そうではありません
The truth is that there was only
a seven-year age difference
実際には ヨセフと年長のルベンとはー
わずか 7歳しか離れていません
between Joseph’s oldest brother,
Reuben, and Joseph himself.
In fact, 11 of Jacob’s sons
ヤコブの息子のうち11人は—
were born
during the seven-year period
彼がラバンのために働いたー
7年のうちに生まれています
when Jacob
was working for Laban.
Eleven sons in seven years,
どうして7年間に11人も
生まれたのでしょうか？
how is that possible?
It’s easy, when you remember
that Jacob had two wives
答えは簡単です
ヤコブには二人の妻と
二人のそばめがいたのです
and two concubines,
or secondary wives.
So there didn’t have to be
a nine-month interval
それで 次の出産までに—
9か月待たなければならない
ということはなかったのです
between the birth
of the children.
In fact, some could have been born
just about at the same time;
実際 同じ年に生まれた
同い年の息子たちもいたことでしょう
they could have been
the same age.
So when Joseph
was sold into slavery at age 17,
それで ヨセフが売られた
17歳のとき—
his oldest brother
was no more than 24.
年長の息子は24歳でした
一つか二つしか年の離れていないー
Some of his brothers were only
a year or two older than Joseph himself.
他の異母兄弟もいたことでしょう
So we’re talking
about a group of young men
ですから それは10代後半からー
in their late teens
and early 20’s,
20代前半の若者のグループでした
and this might explain
some of the hotheaded reactions
そう考えると 幾人かの息子がー
感情的な反応を見せたのもうなずけます
that some
of those young men had.
息子たちについて理解できました
Well, so much for the boys.
What about their father, Jacob?
では 父親のヤコブはどうですか？
What can we learn about him?
何を学べるでしょうか？
A lot.
沢山あります
一つの点として
彼は霊的な人でした
For one thing,
he was a spiritual man.
Now, this is something
for you young brothers and sisters
これは 結婚を真剣に考える
兄弟姉妹にとって参考になるでしょう
who are contemplating
marriage to think about.
Jacob was willing
to go to any length
ヤコブは エホバとの良い関係を
保つために—
to keep his relationship
with Jehovah intact.
あらゆる努力を払いました
Let’s take an example:
創世記 29章18節を
例として取り上げましょう
Genesis 29:18.
You can follow along
on the screen as I read this.
お読みしますので
画面をご覧ください
結婚という観点で読みましょう
And we’re talking
about marriage here.
創世記 29章18節です
Genesis 29:18.
It says:
“Jacob had fallen in love with Rachel,
こうあります
“ヤコブはラケルを愛していた”
“so he said:
‘I am willing to serve you seven years
“それで彼は言った
「あなたの下の娘ラケルのため—”
“わたしは喜んで
あなたに七年仕えます」”
for your younger daughter Rachel.’”
Now what’s the takeaway?
ヤコブはー
それが異教徒であろうと構わず—
Jacob didn’t marry
the first person who came along,
最初に出会う女性と結婚するという
ことはありませんでした
maybe some pagan woman.
“7年も 待てない”
He didn’t say,
‘Well, seven years is too long to wait.
“フィリステア人の女性を見つけて
結婚しよう”などとも—
I’m going to find some Philistine woman,
and I’ll marry her.’
言いませんでした
He was willing to wait
so that he could marry someone
エホバを共に崇拝できる人と
結婚するため喜んで待ったのです
who would join him
in the worship of Jehovah.
若い皆さんも
待つ態度を示すなら—
And you young folks,
if you are willing to wait,
you can be sure that you will have
Jehovah’s blessing as well.
同じようにエホバの祝福を
確信できるでしょう
Now Jacob was apparently also
a bit of a romantic.
ヤコブは ロマンチックな人でも
あったようです
20節に こうあります
Notice verse 20.
”こうしてヤコブはラケルのために
七年間仕えたが—”
It says:
“And Jacob served seven years for Rachel,”
but notice this,
次に注目してください
“but in his eyes
they were like just a few days
”彼女に対する愛ゆえに
それは彼の目にほんの数日のようであった”
because of his love for her.”
Now, isn’t that poetic?
詩的ですね
Jacob may have learned
to treasure his wife
ヤコブは 親のイサクやリベカを見て
妻を慈しむことを学んだでしょう
by observing his parents,
Isaac and Rebekah.
It appears that they
had a strong marriage.
二人の結婚の絆は強固でした
Just notice what we read
そのことは 創世記 26章8節から
明らかです
at Genesis 26:8,
Genesis 26:8.
創世記 26章8節です
“彼のそこでの日数が
延びているときのこと—”
It says:
“After some time had passed,
“Abimelech king of the Philistines
was looking out of the window,
“フィリスティア人の王アビメレクが
窓から外を見て眺めていると—”
and he saw Isaac,”
that’s Jacob’s father,
“そこではイサクが妻のリベカと
楽しく過ごしているのであった”
“displaying affection
for Rebekah his wife.”
So it appears
that Isaac and Rebekah
明らかにイサクとリベカは
温かな結婚の絆で結ばれていました
had a warm relationship,
a good marriage.
さらに ヤコブから
何を学べますか？
Now, what else
can we learn about Jacob?
There’s an interesting detail recorded
25章27節からも
興味深い情報を得られます
in chapter 25 and verse 27.
It says:
“As the boys got bigger, Esau,”
こうあります
“さて 男の子たちは
大きくなってゆき—”
Jacob’s brother,
“[兄の]エサウは狩りの仕方を知る人
野の人となったが—”
“became a skilled hunter,
a man of the field,
“but Jacob was a blameless man,
“ヤコブはとがめのない人で
天幕に住んでいた”
dwelling in tents.”
So Jacob liked to dwell in tents.
ヤコブは 天幕で過ごすのを好みました
That might explain
the strong bond that developed
ヤコブが 末息子のヨセフと
深い絆を育んだ様子が理解できます
between Jacob and Joseph,
who was his youngest for many years.
Now although Jacob
liked to dwell in tents,
もちろん 天幕を好んだからといって—
ヤコブは弱々しい人では
ありませんでした
he was by no means a sissy.
He was a strong man,
but he was a spiritual man.
彼は 強く 何より霊的な人でした
That’s something
for you young brothers to take away.
若い人も 見倣えますね
You want to be strong,
we know you do,
強い人でありたいと思うでしょう
but spirituality
should come first.
でもまず 霊的な人であるべきです
あるとき 霊的な人ヤコブは—
One time, spiritual Jacob
gave his sons a beautiful lesson
家族の中で生じる問題を
解決する方法について—
on how to settle
a difference with a family member.
息子たちに素晴らしい
教訓を与えました
We read about it
at Genesis chapter 32.
それは 創世記 32章に
記録されています
And I think all of us can learn
from his example.
わたしたちすべては
その手本から学べます
We learn at Genesis 32
創世記 32章を見るとー
that Jacob’s brother, Esau,
was coming to see him.
ヤコブの兄弟エサウが
会いにやってきます
Now, they hadn’t seen
each other for 20 years,
非常に難しい問題があったため—
彼らは20年も顔を
合わせていませんでした
and to say that their parting
had been difficult is an understatement.
実際には20年以上前に
彼らは関係を断ちましたが—
The fact is that when they separated
more than 20 years earlier,
エサウは いつか弟のヤコブを
殺すと誓っていました
Esau had vowed that one day
he was going to kill his brother;
そのエサウが会いに来たのです
now he was coming to see him.
Now, why was he
so angry with Jacob?
なぜ それほどの怒りを
ヤコブに抱いていたのでしょうか？
It’s because Jacob had received
a blessing from their father,
それは ヤコブが父親の祝福を
受けたからです
and Esau was not happy.
エサウは 気に入りませんでした
そのエサウが 400人のもの男たちを
引き連れて到着しました
So Esau arrives,
and 400 men are with him.
なぜでしょうか？
Why 400 men?
聖書は何も述べていません
Well, the Bible doesn’t say.
重んじられ 際立った存在になった
ということを—
But it could be
that he was trying to show
how important and prominent
he had become.
示すためだったかもしれません
ヤコブは どのように
反応しましたか？
How did Jacob react?
Did he try to go tit for tat?
いわば しっぺ返しをして—
Did he try to show how important
and prominent he had become
受けた祝福により
自分がどれほど重んじられ—
際立った存在になったかを
示したでしょうか?
with all of the blessings
he’d received?
Did he reopen old wounds?
古傷を暴いたでしょうか?
Did he argue with his brother?
議論をしましたか?
“わたしは最初から正しかった”
Did he say,
‘You know I was right all along,
“間違っていたのは
あなたの方ですよね？”などと—
and you, Esau,
you have been wrong’?
言いましたか？
Did he demand an apology?
謝罪を求めたでしょうか?
No.
いいえ
There was a lot that Jacob
could have bragged about.
ヤコブには誇れることが
たくさんありました
No question about that.
疑問の余地はありません
There was no doubt that Jacob
had Jehovah’s blessing.
疑いなく ヤコブは
エホバの祝福を受けていました
Early on,
we read that an angel of Jehovah
エホバのみ使いが彼に表われて—
had appeared to him
and said:
“わたしは あなたの父—”
“I am Jehovah
“アブラハムの神
イサクの神エホバである”
“the God of Abraham your father
and the God of Isaac.
“The land on which you are lying,
“あなたの横たわっている地—”
“わたしはそれをあなたに
そしてあなたの胤に与える”
“to you I am going to give it
and to your offspring.
“わたしはあなたと共におり—”
“I am with you,
“and I will safeguard you
wherever you go . . .
“その行くすべての道で
あなたを守り—”
I will not leave you.”
“わたしは……あなたを
離れないからである”
Well, that’s quite a blessing,
isn’t it?
素晴らしい祝福です
しかし それだけでは
ありませんでした
But there’s more.
For a portion
of the previous night
ヤコブがエサウと会う
前の晩のこと—
—that is, the night before Esau
and Jacob met up—
ヤコブはみ使いと格闘しました
Jacob had wrestled with an angel,
そして結果として 更に祝福を
受けることになりました
and as a result,
he had managed
to receive another blessing.
でもヤコブは そうした祝福を
見せびらかしたりしませんでした
But Jacob didn’t flaunt
his blessings.
Instead, he humbled himself.
むしろ 謙遜に振る舞いました
In fact, he even bowed down
seven times before his brother
実際ヤコブは 妻たちや
11人の息子たちの前で—
in front of his wives
and his 11 sons.
エサウに 七回も
身をかがめたのです
So Jacob settled
any lingering difference with Esau
ヤコブは エサウとの間の深い溝を
力によってでも—
not with his fists,
not with a bragging tongue,
not with a weapon,
自慢することによってでも
戦いの武器によってでもなく—
but humbly,
like a real man
霊的な人として
謙遜な仕方で解決したのです
—like a real, spiritual man.
In contrast,
how did Jacob’s ten sons
それとは対照的に
彼の10人の息子たちは—
どのように問題を
解決したでしょうか？
settle their difference
with Joseph?
臆病にも 10人でヨセフひとりを
相手にしたのです
Like a bunch of cowards.
It was 10 to 1
against Joseph.
First, they decided
to kill their brother,
最初は 彼を殺そうとしましたが
結局は奴隷として売りました
and then they delivered him
up into slavery.
ねたみに満たされた若者たちは—
Those jealous young men
didn’t learn a thing
父親の素晴らしい霊的な手本からー
from their father’s
excellent spiritual example.
何も学んでいませんでした
もしあなたが 家族の中でー
Well, if you’re on the outs
with a member of your family,
誰かとの関係を損ねていたり—
if you had
a serious difficulty with someone,
深刻な違いを抱えているなら—
could you try to settle the matter
peacefully as Jacob did?
ヤコブのように平和な仕方でー
問題を解決しましょう
もし相手が謝ろうとしているならー
If the person tries to apologize,
be gracious about it.
広い心で接し—
謝りにくい状況を
作らないようにします
Don’t make it difficult
for him to apologize.
Don’t dredge up
過去に生じた些細なことを
持ち出さないにしましょう
all of the unnecessary details
about the past.
You may be in the right,
as Jacob was,
ヤコブのように
あなたの方が正しかったとしても—
but isn’t the important thing
to make peace?
重要なのは
平和を生み出すことです
Jehovah loves the peacemakers.
エホバは 平和を作り出す人を
喜ばれます
Well, what else
do we learn about Jacob?
他にも ヤコブから何を学べますか？
We learn that he wasn’t
his father’s favorite.
彼は 父親のお気に入りという訳では
なかったことがわかります
Let’s look
at Genesis chapter 25,
創世記 25章28節を見てみましょう
verse 28.
“And Isaac loved Esau
“そしてイサクはエサウを愛していた”
“because it meant game in his mouth,
“その口に獲物を
もたらしたからであった”
whereas Rebekah loved Jacob.”
“しかしリベカは
ヤコブを愛する者であった”
Now, this story may resonate
with many of you out there,
もし皆さんが 大きな家族の中で—
大勢の兄弟姉妹に囲まれて
成長してきたとすれば—
especially if you’ve grown up
in a large family
or perhaps you’ve had
a number of brothers and sisters.
この状況を
よく理解できるでしょう
Now, we know
your parents claim
皆さんのご両親は
“どの子も公平に扱っている—”
that they always treated
all of you the same,
that they never ever
had a preference.
“えこひいきなどしない”
と言うでしょう
But ask the kids,
でも子どもたちに—
“誰か親に気に入られている子がいるか？”
と尋ねれば—
Was there anyone in the family
who was the favorite?
They all know.
‘She was!’
きっとみんな知っていて
“あの子！”と答えるでしょう
They know this.
The parents don’t realize it,
but they are giving preferential treatment.
親は気づかないうちに 誰かを
特に可愛がってしまうのです
And so this happens,
and it can be disconcerting at times.
そういうことが生じると
子どもたちは当惑するかもしれません
Imagine this scenario:
こんな状況を考えてみましょう
Imagine that you have a couple
who have two children, two sons.
ある夫婦に二人の息子たちがいました
One is a pioneer.
一人は開拓者です
He has never given his parents
a moment’s grief.
彼は 親を悲しませるような
ことをしません
The other
never accepted the truth,
もう一人は 真理を  受け入れませんでしたが—
but he has done well
in business,
ビジネスで成功を収めました
and as a result,
he has been generous to his parents,
彼は 経済的に両親を
惜しみなく援助し—
and the parents are grateful,
very grateful.
親もそれを非常に
感謝しています
親が その息子のビジネス上の成功を
自慢して話すのを—
And the pioneer
often hears the parents bragging
about the successes
that his brother has had in business.
開拓者の息子は
たびたび耳にします
Well, the pioneer can’t help
the parents materially very much,
開拓者の息子はー
物質面で親を助けることができません
and so he feels that there’s
a bit of partiality there.
それで ちょっと不公平に感じます
Is it hurtful?
辛い状況ですね
Yes.
That is life.
人生には こうしたことが
生じえます
It’s chemistry.
It’s just chemistry.
しかし 開拓者の息子はー
But the pioneer needs to realize
エホバが自分の奉仕を
高く評価してくださり—
that Jehovah God
appreciates his work.
み名のために
行なっていることのゆえに—
His heavenly Father
loves him very much
自分をとても愛しておられる
ことを悟るべきです
for the work
that he is doing for His name.
Now, Jacob must have known
ヤコブの場合 イサクが自分よりも
兄を愛していることを知っていました
that Isaac loved his brother
more than he loved him.
そして 子どもを設けたら
公平に扱おうと心に誓ったことでしょう
And perhaps he vowed
that when he had children,
he would treat them all the same.
Well, if he did,
he didn’t keep that promise, did he?
でも ヤコブは
そうはしなかったようですね
Everyone knew
that Joseph was the favorite.
ヨセフがお気に入りだったことに
みんなが気づいていたからです
Well, have you noticed what we had to do
to make a composite of this family?
さて この家族の全体像をつかむのに
必要なのはどんなことでしたか？
We had to read
from several different chapters of the Bible
幾つかの異なる章を読みました
—Genesis 25, 26, 28, 29, 32.
創世記 25, 26, 28, 29
そして32章です
ある出来事の全体像を把握するには—
You can’t always get
a complete picture of an incident
by reading just one chapter,
just by reading the chapter you are reading.
読んでいるその章だけでは
不十分なことがあります
Sometimes you have to extract details
from other chapters of the Bible.
聖書の他の章から 詳細な情報を
得なければならないこともあるのです
Now let’s consider
one more example
物事の全体像をつかむことが—
where getting the complete picture
can enrich our understanding.
理解を増し加えることを示す例をー
もう一つ 手短に考慮しましょう
This is going to be
a shorter one.
We’re going to consider
the story of Naaman.
ナアマンに生じた出来事です
Now, you remember the story.
皆さんも よくご存じでしょう
At 2 Kings 5:1,
列王第二 5章1節が示すように—
we learn that Naaman
was the chief of the army
ナアマンは シリアの王
ベンハダド二世の軍の長でした
of Ben-hadad II,
the king of Syria.
しかし らい病にかかっていました
But he was a leper.
Now Ben-hadad learned
that there was a prophet in Israel
さて ベンハダドはイスラエルにー
エリシャという預言者がいて—
Elisha who could heal him
of his leprosy.
彼のらい病を癒せることを知ります
And so he told Naaman
that he should go to Israel
それで その預言者のもとに行ってー
癒しを受けるようにナアマンに告げます
and go to the prophet
and get healed.
And so word was sent
to the king of Israel by letter,
そのことはイスラエルの王にも
書面で知らされ—
and the king of Israel was asked
to send Naaman to Elisha.
ナアマンをエリシャに見て
もらえるよう依頼がなされます
しかし イスラエルとシリアが
対立関係にあったことを考えると—
Now, when you think of it,
this was a strange request
because Israel and Syria
were often at odds.
この依頼は奇妙に
聞こえるかもしれません
Sometimes there were
wars between them,
戦い合うことさえあった間柄なのに—
and now, here you have
the king of Syria sending his general,
ここでシリアの王はー
兵を率いる軍の長を遣わして—
the one who is going to head
the army against Israel,
“わたしの軍の長を
もっと元気にしたいので—”
and saying: ‘Well, I’d like my general
to be a more effective general.
“癒してもらえるよう
取り計らってほしい”と頼んだのです
Could you please make sure
that he gets healed?’
Well, somehow,
he’s sent to Elisha
王はエリシャのところへ
行かせ—
and Elisha kindly heals Naaman
エリシャは親切に
ナアマンを癒したのでー
and Naaman becomes
a worshipper of Jehovah.
彼はエホバの崇拝者になりました
Well, we can imagine,
ではここで
想像力を働かせてみましょう
remember we’re talking
about using our imagination,
we can imagine
that when Naaman returned to Syria,
シリアに帰ってきたナアマンを見て—
ベンハダドはどれほどエリシャに
感謝したことでしょう
Ben-hadad had lots of nice things
to say about Elisha.
So then, everyone lived
happily ever after, right?
それで めでたしめでたしということに
なりましたか？
If we didn’t read on,
we might think so.
その先を読まないと
そう思うかもしれません
But that’s not
the end of the story.
実際には それで終わった訳では
ありません
In the next chapter,
chapter 6,
続く6章を読むと ベンハダドが
イスラエルに宣戦布告しています
we learn that Ben-hadad
declared war against Israel.
ナアマンが まだ軍の長であったならー
Now, if Naaman
was still the chief of the army,
彼は難しい立場に立たされたでしょう
he’d be in an awkward position.
Was he going
to lead the armies of Syria
エホバを崇拝する仲間と戦うためにー
against fellow worshippers
of Jehovah?
シリアの軍を率いるのでしょうか？
But it gets worse.
もっと悪いことがおきました
Ben-hadad learns that Elisha
ベンハダドは シリア人の戦略をー
is revealing the Syrians’ war strategies
to the king of Israel,
イスラエルの王に告げているのが
エリシャだと知ると—
彼を捕らえるため大軍を遣わしました
so he sends a large army
to capture Elisha
自分の軍の長を癒した
まさにその人をです
—the very man who
had healed his general.
なんという感謝の表われでしょう
So much for gratitude.
Now, it’s interesting
that Naaman is not mentioned
興味深いのは
軍を率いる長として—
ナアマンの名前が
挙げられていないことです
as being at the head
of those armies.
Did he get out of it somehow?
どうにかして
身を引いたのでしょうか？
Don’t ask me.
わたしに聞かないでください
If he’s resurrected,
you’ll have to ask him.
復活してきたら本人に
聞いてみてください
What lesson can we learn?
何を学べますか？
That the gratitude of the world
is fleeting.
世が示す感謝は
すぐに消えゆくものです
Some of us may get excited
if there’s a favorable article
新聞やテレビで エホバの証人に関するー
about Jehovah’s Witnesses
in a newspaper
好意的なコメントが報じられると—
or if some TV personality
makes a kind statement about us.
ある人は興奮するかもしれません
But what did Jehovah God say?
エホバは何とおっしゃっていますか？
Genesis 3:15:
創世記 3章15節には—
“I will put enmity
between you and the woman.”
“わたしは お前と女との間に
敵意を置く”とあります
So Jehovah’s organization
and Satan’s organization
ですから エホバの組織と
サタンの組織は—
are always going to be at odds.
絶えず対立しているのです
聖書通読は 退屈なものではなく
喜びをもたらします
Bible reading isn’t a chore.
It’s a joy.
Get the whole picture
of what you’re reading,
読んでいることの全体像をつかむなら
一層喜びが増すでしょう
and you’ll enjoy it even more.
We wish you all
Jehovah’s rich blessing
この聖なる書物への感謝を
深めてゆかれる皆さんを—
as you continue
to enhance your appreciation
エホバが豊かに
祝福してくださるよう願っています
for this sacred volume.
And now, let’s turn to Rocky.
では ロッキーに替わりましょう
I think Rocky
has some practical application to share.
実際的な適用について
扱ってくださいます
Thank you, and as David mentioned,
ありがとうございます
デービッドが指摘したとおり—
there is a close connection between joy
喜びは 聖書通読をどのように行うかに
深く関係しています
and how we handle our Bible reading.
In this dramatization,
we meet a pioneer sister
次のドラマでは
一人の開拓者の姉妹が—
who did everything just right
なすべきことを行っているのにー
but still felt
that her motivation was declining.
やる気が薄らいでいくことに気づきます
開拓者でも そうでなくても—
Whether you pioneer or not,
notice the importance
of properly digesting
霊的食物を正しく消化することの
重要性にご注目ください
our vital spiritual food.
That’s my roommate, Camille.
ルームメイトのカミールです
そして あの...
And, well,
これがわたしです
that’s me.
I haven’t felt like myself recently.
最近 なぜか気分がさえないんです
I started regular pioneering
a couple of years ago.
数年前に開拓奉仕を始めて—
At first, I was really zealous.
最初はすごく奉仕に熱心だったのに—
だんだん 初めの熱意が
なくなってしまった...
But somewhere down the line,
I lost that good feeling.
そして すべてに
喜びが無くなってしまったわ
Soon, I was losing my joy
for almost everything.
正直 何が間違っているか
分からなかった
I honestly didn’t know
what was wrong.
何も悪いことをしている
わけじゃないし...
It wasn’t like I was doing
anything bad.
I thought,
“きっと疲れているだけ” と思ってた
‘Maybe I’m just tired.’
But it wasn’t getting better.
でも全然良くならない
わたしに何が起きたか考えてみたわ
I tried to assess
what was going on with myself.
I felt love for Jehovah.
エホバに対する愛も—
会衆への愛も感じている
I felt love for the congregation,
but I felt unmotivated in my service.
でも奉仕の意欲がわかないんです
I felt like something was missing.
何かが足りないと感じてた
As my enthusiasm waned,
熱意が弱まると
集会の出席もおろそかになっていったわ
my meeting attendance suffered too.
Thankfully, the loving elders
in my congregation noticed,
ありがたいことに
会衆の愛ある長老が気づいて—
すぐに援助に来て下さった
and help was on the way.
わたしがどうしているか
兄弟たちは見に来られたの
The brothers visited
to see how I was doing.
They really listened to me,
わたしの話によく耳を傾けてから—
霊的な習慣を尋ねて下さった
and they asked about
my spiritual routine.
聖書は毎日読んでいたけど—
Well, I read the Bible every day,
but, I admitted,
I’m not a natural study person.
読書はあまり好きな方ではないと
認めたわ
するとイエスの母マリアの例を
思い起こさせて下さったの
They reminded me
about the example of Mary,
Jesus’ mother.
At first, I didn’t see the link,
初めは関連が分からなかったけど—
but as we read from the Bible,
it became more clear.
聖書を読んでいくうちに
明らかになっていったわ
Mary was known
for being a faithful woman.
マリアは信仰の女性として
知られているけど—
その信仰を強めたものは
何だったのかしら？
But what kept her faith strong?
マリアは霊的に意義深い言葉に
注意を払い—
The Bible account said
that Mary paid careful attention
聞いた事柄をじっくりと黙想し—
to words that had
deep spiritual meaning
“心の中であれこれと
結論を下しつつ—”
and later took time to meditate,
“こうして語られる事柄すべてを
記憶にとどめていった”と—
“drawing conclusions in her heart.”
聖書は述べている
By meditating on spiritual things,
マリアは霊的な事柄を
黙想することによって—
Mary strengthened her faith
and zeal for serving Jehovah.
エホバに対する信仰と熱意を強めていた
分かったわ
I understand now.
わたしは読んだことを黙想する時間を
取っていなかったから—
I was reading spiritual food,
but I wasn’t taking time to digest it,
心の中の動機になっていなかったのね
so it wasn’t sinking
down into my heart.
As a result,
I was on a direct path
すぐに何かを変えなければ—
霊的に燃え尽きてしまう
ところだったわ
to spiritual burnout
if I didn’t change something quick!
I began by taking control
of my busy schedule.
まずは忙しい予定を調整して—
一日を聖書通読で始めることにしたわ
I made it a priority
to start my day with Bible reading.
I sought out quiet places
そして静かな場所で
読んだ事柄を黙想するの
where I could meditate on what I read.
Meaningful Bible study reinvigorated
意義深い黙想によって—
エホバにお仕えしたいという
熱意はよみがえり—
my passion for serving Jehovah,
祈りのこもった黙想は—
and prayerful meditation
わたしの焦点を元通りに
合わせてくれたわ
helped me to refocus.
Over time,
making these changes
調整してから—
エホバへの奉仕の喜びを
徐々に取り戻したわ
helped me to find joy
in my service to Jehovah again.
聖書が述べる通り—
The Bible says when we make time
霊的な事柄を読み
黙想する時間を取り分けるなら—
to read and meditate on spiritual things,
we will become
“like a tree planted by streams of water,”
わたしたちは 水のほとりに
植えられた木のようになり—
その葉は枯れることがなく—
with foliage that never withers.
行なうことはすべて成功する！
And everything we do will succeed.
姉妹が聖書を毎日読んでいたことに
お気づきでしたか？
Did you notice that our sister
read the Bible every day?
But that alone did not give her
the spiritual sustenance she needed.
しかしそれだけで必要な霊的栄養素を
とれるわけではありません
We don’t want our Bible reading
to become an automatic process.
聖書通読を 無意識に行なう習慣に
しないでください
What does that mean
—automatic process?
無意識に行なうとは
どういうことでしょうか？
Well, breathing, walking,
or perhaps, riding a bicycle
例えば わたしたちは
特に考えなくても—
息をしたり歩いたり
自転車に乗ったりすることができます
are things many can do
without even thinking.
They become automatic processes.
いわば 無意識に行っているのです
To some extent,
this is also true of reading.
同じことが読むことにも
生じえます
So, what can help us
develop the art of meditation?
では どうすれば黙想を
効果的に行なえますか？
When you finish reading a passage,
ある部分を読み終わったなら
いったん読むのをやめ—
you might pause
and ponder over what you have just read
読んだ事を正しく理解しているかどうか
思い巡らしましょう
to be sure
that you understand it correctly.
Ask yourself:
こう自問します
‘What does this
teach me about Jehovah?
“ここから エホバについて
何を学べるだろうか？”
‘How can I apply this in my life?
“自分の生活にどのように
適用できるだろうか？”
Or how can I use this
in my field ministry?’
“野外宣教でどのように
活用できるだろうか？”
You should always make sure
to apply what you read.
読んだことを
適用するようにしましょう
また 気を散らすものの少ない環境で
読むことも集中する助けになります
And remember,
reading in a stress-free environment
with few distractions
helps our concentration.
But what if our attention span is short
では 注意を集中できる時間が短く—
and our mind starts to wander quickly?
すぐに思いがさまよい始めるならー
Starting out with shorter study sessions
どうすればよいでしょうか？
and gradually lengthening them
have helped some.
短い時間から初めてー
徐々に長くするという方法が—
Our goal should be to linger in study,
助けになるかもしれません
学んでいることに留まるよう努め
急いで通り過ぎないようにします
not to rush through it.
That’s when our spiritual food
becomes the refreshment we need.
そうすれば 霊的な食物から
爽やかさを得るでしょう
Some excellent tools
when meditating are the illustrations
黙想のための優れた道具は
出版物に乗せられる挿絵や写真です
and photographs
we find in our publications.
例として ダニエル5章の記述を
取り上げましょう
Take the Bible account
found in Daniel chapter 5 as an example.
It reads: “That very night
こうあります
“まさしくその夜
カルデア人の王ベルシャザルは殺され—”
“Belshazzar
the Chaldean king was killed.
“メディア人ダリウスが
その王国を受けた”
“And Darius the Mede
received the kingdom;
“ダリウスはおよそ六十二歳であった”
he was about 62 years old.”
Using other scriptures
that provide additional details,
この出来事に関する預言を含め—
聖書の様々な記述を用いて
詳細を理解することにより—
including prophecies about the event,
the Art Department
at world headquarters
世界本部のアート部門は—
was able to paint a vivid picture
of what it may have been like that night,
鮮やかな絵で
その夜の様子を描き出しました
それは メディア-ペルシャの兵士たちが
ユーフラテス川の川底を進み—
when the Medo-Persian soldiers
waded through the Euphrates River
and entered the city of Babylon
through its open gates.
開かれていた門を通って
バビロンの都市に入る様子です
Now, we know that looking up
illustrations in our literature
出版物にある挿絵を見ることは
黙想の助けになります
can be a helpful tool when meditating.
しかし なぜそう言えるのでしょうか?
But why is that the case?
では アート部門の舞台裏を見て
その答えを見いだしましょう
Let’s go behind the scenes
of the Art Department and find out.
A visual aid often makes
a clearer
視覚教材は大抵
話す言葉よりも鮮明で—
or more lasting impression
on the mind than does the spoken word.
いつまでも残る印象を与えます
Under the direction
of the Writing Committee,
アート部門は40年近くにわたって—
the Art Department
has enjoyed
執筆委員会の指示のもとー
the privilege of designing
and illustrating Bible literature
聖書文書をデザインし準備してきました
for almost 40 years.
The department was established
sometime before 1976.
この部門が設けられたのは
1976年より 少し前のことですがー
But a small team of artists
had been working
on illustrations and typography
「創造の写真劇」の頃には
すでに少人数のアーティストたちが—
from as far back
as the “Photo-Drama of Creation.”
挿絵や活版印刷に携わっていました
聖書文書を出版する業は
大きな変化を経てきました
The work of publishing Bible literature
has seen many changes.
Now there are EPUBs, interactive PDFs,
今では EPUB形式や
インタラクティブなPDFファイル
Web design, and HTML content,
ウェブデザインや
HTML形式などがあります
all of which require new skills
これらすべてには
新しい技術が求められ—
ベテル内の多くの部門との
密な協力関係が必要です
as well as close collaboration
with many other Bethel departments.
The Art Department
is structured into teams.
アート部門は
いくつかのチームで構成されており—
Each team is made up
of designers, photographers,
各チームには
デザイナーやカメラマン
illustrators, prop and set makers,
挿絵画家
美術スタッフ
costume and makeup artists,
衣装・メイク係
as well as production workers.
そして 生産スタッフがいます
チームリーダーと
スケジュール管理者は—
The team lead and the scheduler
work directly
執筆部門コンタクトの編集者と
直接やり取りします
with the Writing Department contact
known as a compiler.
After receiving
an early version of the text,
テキストの草案を受け取ると—
３人の兄弟たちが その目的と
デザイン案について話し合います
the three brothers discuss
the purpose
and possible look of the design.
All on the team
are invited to collaborate
コンセプトがまとまってくると
チームの全員が集められ—
as concepts are developed.
Each member contributes
to the overall design of a project.
プロジェクトの大まかな案に
それぞれが貢献します
Before any production work is started,
実際の作業を始める前に
コンセプトをスケッチしてまとめます
concepts are sketched and developed.
These sketches become a blueprint
このスケッチを見て
チームはコンセプトを理解し—
that helps the team
understand the concept,
plan the resources,
材料を決め—
and ensure
that the project stays on track.
プロジェクトが
本題からそれないようにします
Who is the target audience?
対象となるのは だれなのか—
How will this publication be used?
この出版物は
どのように用いられるのか—
The design should be clear and simple.
シンプルで わかりやすいデザインを—
And it needs to work in all languages.
すべての言語で提供します
This is no small task.
簡単なことではありません
When the design is ready,
デザインが準備できると—
the compiler presents a mock-up
of the publication
編集者は 出版物の試作品を
執筆委員会に提出します
to the Writing Committee.
The committee reviews the design
and makes any needed adjustments.
委員会は デザインを確認し
必要な調整をします
コンセプトが承認されるとー
After the concept is approved,
production begins.
制作が始まります
Around the world,
there are many photographers
世界中にいる大勢のカメラマンが—
画像を提供する奉仕を
パートタイムでしています
who work part-time to assist
in providing images.
Photographs are also taken in our studio
写真撮影は スタジオや
そのほかの場所でも行なわれます
and other locations.
These images help give our publications
an international look.
このような写真により
出版物に国際的な彩りが添えられます
Accuracy is vital.
正確さは肝要です
A researcher provides
historical references and inspiration.
調査する人は
歴史的資料やアイデアを提供します
Hair, makeup, and costumes
髪型や—
メイク また 衣装を—
時代背景や地域に合わせて
デザインします
are designed to depict
the time period and region.
Props, set design, and lighting
小道具や大道具 照明によって—
それらしい背景が出来上がります
provide the right look and setting.
When combined,
それぞれの要素が組み合わさると
ストーリーができあがり—
each element helps tell the story
and capture the imagination of the viewer.
見る人の注意を引きつけます
Sets are also built in 3D programs.
3Dで背景を組むこともあります
They can be used as art source
美術的資料としたり—
or as final illustrations.
最終的な挿絵として用います
Whether painted digitally
or with traditional materials,
デジタル的か
本来の原料で描くかに関わらず—
the artist renders the illustration
画家は最終的な使用に沿うかたちで
挿絵を描きます
in a style suited for its final use.
When design meets illustration,
インフォグラフィックスと呼ばれる
図と挿絵を合わせたものもあります
infographics are born.
After final approval
by the Writing Committee,
執筆委員会から最終承認が下りると—
files are sent to the printeries
ファイルは プリンタリーや
ウェブサイトに送られるか
and to the website
or used to create other digital versions.
デジタル版作成のために
使われます
In order to reach the hearts of those
who read a Bible-based publication,
聖書に基づく出版物を読む人の
心に達するためには—
hands and hearts
have to be involved in its creation.
実際に手を使い 心を込めなければ
この仕事は行なえません
Those of us in the Art Department
アート部門にいる わたしたちは—
最も緊急な業をサポートできることを
特権だと感じています
consider it a privilege to give support
to the most urgent of all work
それは 良いたよりを宣べ伝える業です
—preaching the good news.
Did you notice
the answer to our question,
質問の答えが見いだせましたか？
Why can looking up illustrations
in our literature be helpful?
なぜ 出版物の挿絵を見ることは
助けになるのでしょうか？
As the narrator said, “A visual aid
ナレーターが語っていた通り—
“視覚教材は大抵
話す言葉よりも鮮明で—”
“often makes a clearer
or more lasting impression on the mind
“いつまでも残る
印象を与え”るからです
than does the spoken word.”
But on top of that,
加えて 挿絵により
その出来事が生き生きとよみがえります
illustrations
can help a story come alive.
They help us
envision an event before our eyes
生じた出来事を目の前に
思い描くことで—
and thus deepen our appreciation
for Bible truths
聖書の真理や エホバ神への
感謝を深めることができるのです
and ultimately for Jehovah God.
While illustrations and photographs
can be a great complement,
挿絵や写真が
大きな助けになるとはいえ—
霊的な食物の源は
書き記された神の言葉そのものです
it’s the written Word, God’s Word,
that is the source
of the spiritual food.
But what if we face a situation
in which we have access to nothing?
しかし 仮にー
これらすべてを用いることがー
できない状況におかれるとしたら
どうでしょうか
We are not allowed
to have a Bible,
聖書を持つことができずー
no literature with illustrations,
挿絵の載った出版物も
ビデオも 録音物もないとしたらです
no videos,
and no audio recordings.
What do we do?
どうしますか
Our recollection
of what we have read in the past
以前に読んだことを
思い起こすことによりー
霊性を保つことができます
can keep our spirituality intact.
ロシアの一人の兄弟はー
One of our brothers from Russia
faced such a situation.
そのような状況に直面しました
何が助けになったかに注目しましょう
Notice what helped him.
The year was 1963.
それは1963年のことです
I was 36 at the time.
わたしは36歳でした
The KGB searched my home
and found some Bible literature
KGBはわたしの家の中を捜索し—
幾らかの聖書文書と伝道者の
奉仕報告を見つけました
and some publishers’ field service reports.
So I was sentenced
to five years of imprisonment
わたしは活動を組織したかどで
5年の刑を言い渡されました
for being an organizer.
投獄はこれで3度目でした
That was the third time
I had been imprisoned.
Some brothers and sisters
and I went to the court
ウラジミール兄弟を励ますため
数人の兄弟姉妹が法廷に行きました
to support Brother Vladimir.
わたしたちを見ると兄弟は手を握り締め
“大丈夫です”と言いました
When he saw us,
he clasped his hands
and declared,
“Everything is fine!”
A KGB officer told me
KGBの役人が言うには
わたしが投獄されないのは—
that the only reason
I hadn’t been imprisoned
わたしには6人の子どもがいるが—
was because I had six children.
ウラジミールは独身だからでした
But Vladimir was single.
I was just glad
that they had arrested me and not him,
家族がいなかったので—
わたしが投獄されて
よかったと思います
because I didn’t have a family.
収容所では聖書も聖書文書も
全くありませんでした
In the camp, I didn’t have a Bible
or any Bible literature at all.
それまでに学んだ知識で
やっていくしかありませんでした
All I had to keep me going
was the knowledge I already had.
兄弟のために祈り あいさつや
励みとなるメッセージを—
We prayed for him,
and we sent greetings
and encouraging messages
to him through his relatives.
兄弟の親族を通して送りました
厳しい検閲のため—
Due to the strict censorship
in the camp,
手紙には互いに励まし合うための
霊的なことは一切書けませんでした
we were not allowed
to write anything spiritual in our letters
to encourage each other.
そうしたとしても
手紙は没収されたでしょう
If we did,
the letters were confiscated.
でもわたしはミハイル兄弟に—
But I really wanted to send Brother Mikhail
something encouraging.
何か励みになるものを
贈りたいと願っていました
収容所ではほかの収容者と
一緒に花を育てていました
I was growing flowers
with a group of inmates in the camp.
So instead of a sending him a letter,
それで手紙の代わりに
花のブーケを贈ることにしました
I decided to send him
a bouquet of flowers.
ウラジミールの姉妹のオルガが
家にやって来て—
Vladimir’s sister Olga came to our home,
ウラジミールからの
きれいな花のブーケをー
and she brought me a beautiful bouquet
of flowers from Vladimir.
届けてくれました
I couldn’t believe
that I had received fresh flowers
有刺鉄線の向こうの収容所の中から
生の花束を受け取るとは—
from behind a barbed-wire fence
—from inside the camp.
全く信じがたいことでした
I was so touched
by his act of kindness
彼の親切な行ないに
心を打たれたわたしはー
that my heart moved me
to write down some verses,
数節の詩を作り
それに“ブーケ”という題をつけました
a poem,
which I called “The Bouquet.”
My relatives came
and visited me in the prison
親族が収容所のわたしを
訪ねてくれたとき—
and delivered to me the poem.
その詩を届けてくれました
I kept the poem
in a very secret place.
その詩は秘密の場所に
隠しておきました
It could have been confiscated,
それは神に関するものでしたから
没収され 処罰されかねませんでした
and I could have been punished
because it was about God.
After Vladimir was released from prison,
ウラジミールは釈放後—
well, he told me that my poem
had really strengthened him
わたしの詩によって
本当に強められたことやー
秘密の隠し場所から
それを取り出しては—
and that he had often taken it out
幾度も幾度も読み返したことを
話してくれました
of its secret hiding place
to read it over and over again.
If it hadn’t been for the support
I received from Jehovah
友の祈りやエホバからの支えが
なかったなら—
and the prayers of friends,
わたしがエホバに仕えることは
もっと難しいものになっていたはずです
it would have been much harder
for me to serve my time.
受け取った詩は自分が友から
また最も重要なことにエホバから—
The poem that I had received
helped me not to feel
separated from my friends
切り離されてはいないことを
感じさせてくれました
and, most importantly,
from Jehovah.
So many years have now gone by.
あれからずいぶん経ちましたが—
難しい時期を切り抜けて
しっかりと立ち続け—
But we have remained firm
through the difficult times,
and we continue serving Jehovah.
今もエホバに仕えています
最近はウラジミールと
電話で連絡をとるようにしていますが—
Lately, Vladimir and I have been trying
to keep in touch by phone,
but we haven’t seen each other
for seven years.
この7年間 互いに会っていません
ウラジミールに
また会いたい気持ちでいっぱいです
I would really love
to see Vladimir again.
わたしが訪問することにしたことを
彼は知りません
He doesn’t know
that I’ve decided to go and visit him.
びっくりして喜んでくれると思います
I hope that he likes the surprise.
“I see these flowers,
grown by hands
丹精込めて咲かせた花
“Hardened from work
that prison demands.
労役で荒れた手によって咲かせた花
“My friend has sent a bouquet.
友が贈ってくれたブーケ
“Prison three times
prevented our meeting,
三度 会うことはかなわなかった
“But you found a way
to convey a greeting.
あなたは挨拶を送る手立てを見出した
“My joy now moves me to say:
わたしは喜びに満たされて言おう
“‘Greetings, my brother,
with all of my heart.
“わたしの兄弟へー”
“心を込めて あいさつを送ろう”
“‘You gave me strength,
although we’re apart.
“離れていてもあなたは強めてくれた”
“‘While you have
countless trials withstood,
“幾多の試練のただ中で
力を尽くし 強めてくれた”
“‘You’ve strengthened me
as best you could.
“‘Greetings, my friend
on that narrow road,
“狭い通路にいる友よ
あいさつを送ろう”
“‘You were always with me
through hardships untold.
“多くの苦難のただ中で
わたしたちはいつも一緒だった”
“‘We worked so hard
for spiritual treasure.
“霊的な宝のために共に力を尽くした”
“‘Blessed we were
for sticking together.
“二人の固いきずなは祝福そのもの”
“‘Cruelly, my friend,
you were taken from me
“わが友は 無残にも引き放されー”
“‘When they tried
to break our integrity.
“我々の忠誠は打ち砕かれようとした”
“‘But God stood by us
and helped us to cope.
“しかし 神は立ち上がり
助けてくださる”
“‘Conquer the evil, we did,
for our dear Kingdom hope.
“我々は悪を征服し
王国の希望のために戦った”
“‘How grateful we are
and always will be
“感謝に満たされ
これからも感謝をささげよう”
“‘For spiritual vision
by which we can see
“‘The crown of life
promised to those
“将来の霊的な希望のゆえに—”
“自ら忠節の道に留まる者に
約束された命の冠のゆえに”
“‘Who stay on the loyal course
they chose.
“‘How much you’ve endured,
long-suffering friend.
“辛抱強い友よ
あなたはどれほど耐え忍んだか”
“‘But Jehovah’s mercy
will never end.
“エホバの憐れみは決して絶えない”
“‘On a paradise earth
our hands will unite,
”地上のパラダイスで手を取り合い
エホバの目を楽しませる花を咲かせよう”
“‘Planting more flowers
to gladden His sight.
“‘Christ Jesus will heal us
during his reign,
“キリスト・イエスはわたしたちを癒し
罪は跡形もなくなるであろう”
“‘So no trace of sin
will ever remain.
“‘And far from the trials
that we overcame,
“耐え抜いた試練を忘れ去り—”
Forever we’ll praise
Jehovah’s great name!’”
“とこしえにわたって
エホバの偉大なみ名を賛美しよう”
真の友はエホバからの祝福です
True friends are such a blessing
from Jehovah,
and you don’t really know
who they are until disaster strikes.
そして誰が真の友かは
災いの時に明らかになります
真理の道を歩んできた人生において—
During my whole life,
walking in the way of the truth,
わたしはよく詩編 119編63節の
次の言葉を考えます
I have often thought
about the words of Psalm 119:63,
“わたしはあなたを真に恐れる
すべての者たちの—”
where it says:
“I am a friend of all who fear you
“また あなたの命令を守る者たちの
仲間なのです”
and of those who keep your orders.”
Our serving side by side
in the Kingdom work
共に王国の業を行なうとき
わたしたちの友情は強くなります
has strengthened our friendship.
永遠に続くのは
そのような友情だけです
It is only that sort of friendship
that will last forever!
What a beautiful friendship!
素晴らしい友情ですね!
Our brotherhood truly is
a blessing from Jehovah.
わたしたちの兄弟関係は
まさにエホバからの祝福です
Brother Mikhail Savitsky spent many years
as a circuit overseer,
ミハイル・サビツキー兄弟は
長年にわたりシベリアやカフカス北部—
helping the Kingdom work progress
in Siberia, northern Caucasus,
さらにはグルジアやアルメニアで
巡回奉仕に携わり —
王国の業の進展を助けてきました
and the countries
of Georgia and Armenia.
In 1992, he had the privilege
of being one of those
1992年 兄弟は—
ロシアでの業の法的認可に関する書面にー
who signed the documents that confirmed
legal recognition of our work in Russia.
署名する特権にあずかりました
However, we regret to inform you
残念なことに
このビデオの制作から程なくして—
that some time
after this segment was produced,
ウラジミール・バルクホリック兄弟は
死の眠りにつきました
Brother Vladimir Varkholik
fell asleep in death.
He was 88 years old
88歳で 59年以上に渡って
エホバに忠実に仕えました
and had served Jehovah faithfully
for over 59 years.
At the time of his death,
亡くなる段階で
26年間開拓者としてー
he had served as a pioneer
for some 26 years
43年間会衆の長老として
奉仕しました
and as an elder
in the congregation for 43 years.
From his interview,
you can clearly see the faith
このインタビューから
明らかなように—
投獄されている12年間—
that kept his spirituality strong
through 12 years of imprisonment.
兄弟はその信仰ゆえに
霊的な強さを保てました
And he is a good example for us.
わたしたちの良い手本です
Did you notice one aspect
of his circumstances while incarcerated?
兄弟が投獄されていた様子について
お気づきになりましたか？
He said:
兄弟は “収容所では 聖書も
聖書文書も全くありませんでした”
“In the camp,
I didn’t have a Bible
“or any Bible literature at all.
“それまでに学んだ知識で
やっていくしかありませんでした”とー
“All I had to keep me going
was the knowledge I already had.”
語っていました
That could happen to us.
同じことは
わたしたちにも生じえます
When persecution starts,
we need to be prepared.
迫害のために備えをしておく
必要があります
That’s one reason
why it is so important
そのためにも
時が許されている限り—
not to neglect
our study of the Bible
聖書の研究を
おろそかにすべきではありません
while we have the opportunity.
Now, back to David.
では デービッドと
代わります
Thanks, Rocky.
We’re truly sorry to hear about Vladimir.
ありがとうございました
ウラジミール兄弟のことを
残念に思います
But one thing is certain,
we know that Jehovah God will not forget
しかし エホバ神がそのみ名のために
兄弟が示した愛を—
the love that he showed for His name.
決してお忘れにならないのは確かです
That was a moving interview indeed.
心を動かされるインタビューでした
Well, back in June,
さて 6月に新しい王国の歌が何曲か
電子的に配信されました
a number of new Kingdom songs
were released electronically,
but one was missing—number 151.
しかし151番だけが抜けていました
Now, you noticed that, didn’t you?
お気づきでしょう
I know you did because nothing escapes
the eagle eyes of you brothers and sisters.
兄弟姉妹の目が節穴ではないことは
わかっています
ではここで151番をご紹介しましょう
Well, here it is, number 151.
It’s entitled
“The Revealing of God’s Sons.”
主題は
“神の子たちが表わし示される”です
And it reminds us
that the time is getting near
残りの者たちが 天に行くときが
近づいていることを—
when the anointed
will hear the final call.
思い起こさせる歌です
では 聞きましょう
Let’s listen.
The time is near when God reveals
His faithful chosen ones.
In heaven they will rule with Christ
As mighty spirit sons.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
And soon the last remaining ones
Will hear his final call.
The King of kings and Lord of lords
Will then collect them all.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
And then with Christ, these sons of God
Will wage the final war.
The joyous marriage to the Lamb
Will last forevermore.
The sons of God will be revealed
Along with Christ, their Lord.
They’ll join him in his victory
And share in his reward.
Don’t you think that was
a beautiful song, Rocky?
美しい歌でしたね！
本当ですね
Absolutely!
That was one beautiful song.
本当に美しい歌です
ものみの塔のコーラス隊には
本当に感謝しています
You know, I really do appreciate
the Watchtower chorus.
Only two or three of them
have professional training,
プロの訓練を受けているのは
2-3人で—
他の皆さんは ひたすら努力して
これほどまでになりました
and the rest have got where they are
just through hard work.
So this is something
that all of us can keep in mind.
その点に注目できます
わたしたちも
歌を練習し 練習し 練習し—
Practice, practice, practice singing.
王国会館で
大きな声で歌いましょう
And then when you
get to the Kingdom Hall, sing out.
終わりが近づいているので
本当に時宜にかなった歌だといえます
And it’s a very timely song,
considering how close we are to the end.
And I’m sure all of you agree that the closer
we are to the end of this system of things,
この体制の終わりが近づくにつれ
野外宣教でなすべきことは多くあります
the more work there is
in the field ministry.
しかし 仕事のために
家ではほとんど会えない人々もいます
But there are individuals whom we
rarely find home due to their secular work.
ヨーロッパの兄弟姉妹はそうした人々に
達する方法を見つけました
In Europe, our brothers
and sisters have found a way
to reach one such group.
Every year, thousands of truck drivers
from all over the world
毎年 世界中から来た
何千人ものトラック運転手が—
ヨーロッパ大陸を縦横に走っています
crisscross the European continent.
家族の生計を立てるため
懸命に働き—
They work hard to make ends meet
for their families
数週間家を離れることも
珍しくありません
but often have to spend
weeks away from home.
Jesus and his apostles
approached people wherever they were.
イエスと弟子たちは人が
どこにいようと近づきました
わたしたちも同じ願いを持っています
It is this same spirit
that must motivate us.
By trying to reach truck drivers
wherever they can be found,
どこでも運転手のいる場所へ行き—
そうしなければ会えない人も含め—
we can make sure
that everyone receives a witness,
すべての人が証言を受けるよう
努力が払われています
even those who would
otherwise be missed.
We live in the Rotterdam area
which has a lot of truck traffic.
トラックの多い
ロッテルダムに住んでいます
We cover our regular territory
once every three months,
通常の区域は3か月に1度
網羅していますが—
while these truck drivers
are hardly ever reached.
トラック運転手にはめったに会えません
We noticed that 300,000 trucks
crossed France every year.
毎年30万台のトラックが
フランスを横断しており—
Thus, it was necessary to explore
この大きな可能性のある分野を
開拓する必要がありました
this formidable potential for the ministry.
Many truck drivers use truck stops
たくさんの運転手が駐車場で
休憩し 泊まっています
to take a short break
or even spend the night there.
宣教に絶好の場所です
That’s ideal for preaching.
While we are parked here, resting,
駐車している間 休憩や洗車をします
we are cleaning the trucks;
we are washing our clothes
because there is no laundry here;
ここには洗濯場がないので
衣類を洗っています
and also we do our cooking.
料理もします
ある日 フランスに行く途中—
One day on my way to France,
オーストリアで車を停めて
運転を交代しました
I had to stop in Austria
to swap drivers.
同僚はトイレに行き
わたしは一人でした
My colleague went to the bathroom,
and I was alone.
その時 証人がやって来て
雑誌を勧めてきたんです
At that moment, a Witness came
and offered me a magazine.
Much effort is being put into reaching
truck drivers in an organized way.
証言が組織的に行なわれるよう
多くの努力が払われています
We made sure all truck stops
were mapped
すべての駐車場を地図にして—
and organized schedules so that pioneers
開拓者が一日に一度はこの区域で
証言できるよう計画を立てています
can preach in this territory
at least once a day.
Publishers will encounter
many different nationalities and languages.
奉仕者は多くの国籍や
言語の人に出会います
言語の壁は最も大きな障害です
The language barrier
is one of the biggest challenges.
On any given morning,
you can encounter
午前だけでルーマニア語
ロシア語—
up to ten different languages:
Romanian, Russian, Polish.
ポーランド語など
10言語に出くわします
When I looked at the magazine,
I saw that it was a Watchtower,
雑誌を見ると
ドイツ語の「ものみの塔」でした
but I thought it was in German.
ドイツ語を話せないと言うと—
I told this brother
that I did not speak German.
その兄弟は車のナンバープレートを見て
ルーマニア語であることに気付きました
Then he had a look at my license plate
and saw that it was Romanian.
He again offered me
the magazine and told me:
“ルーマニア語の雑誌です どうぞ”と
もう一度雑誌を勧めてくれました
“It is Romanian.
It is for you.”
When I saw it,
I was very happy.
とても嬉しかったです
I took the magazine
and was very glad.
喜んで雑誌を受け取りました
もちろん 1世紀のクリスチャンのように
異言は話せませんが—
Of course, we don’t speak in tongues
like the first-century Christians did.
jw.orgのおかげで
どんな言語でも証言できます
But jw.org makes us feel like
we can preach in any language.
We need to go further
than just distributing publications.
出版物を配布する以上のことが必要です
We need to be real teachers,
and to do that,
真の教え手になるために
ビデオを活用しています
we can make use of the videos.
ある運転手はダッシュボードの上に
聖書を広げたまま—
A driver had his Bible
wide open on his dashboard
「聖書を学ぶべきなのはなぜですか」の
ビデオを見て声をあげて泣きました
and literally cried when he watched
the video Why Study the Bible?
Since truck drivers spend
most of their time on the road,
トラック運転手はほとんどの時間を
道路の上で過ごすため—
it is a real challenge to follow up
on those who have shown any interest.
関心を示した人に再び会うことは
容易ではありません
再訪問し研究を始めることは
非常に難しいと感じます
It’s very difficult to do return visits
or to start Bible studies.
You just don’t know when you will meet
a truck driver again.
いつまた会えるかわかりません
So we try to get their e-mail addresses
as soon as possible.
それですぐにメールアドレスを
聞くようにしています
結果は驚くべきものでした
The results were remarkable.
For example, in the last service year,
例えば昨奉仕年度中
約10万冊の雑誌が配布され—
about 100,000 magazines were placed,
100 Bible studies were started,
100件の研究が始まり
4千回ビデオを見せることができました
and 4,000 videos were shown.
Experience shows
that even if it’s not possible
たとえメールアドレスを
聞けなかったとしても—
to obtain an e-mail address,
少しの証言が大きな影響を
与えうることを経験は示しています
the slightest witness given
can have a great impact.
In time, I returned to Romania.
やがてルーマニアに戻りました
I started a Bible study,
progressed spiritually, got married,
聖書研究を始め 霊的に成長し—
結婚して 今はバプテスマを
受けていない伝道者です
and now I am
an unbaptized publisher.
The brother that first
contacted me has no idea.
最初にわたしに接した兄弟は
知らないでしょう
Hebrews 6:11 invites us all
ヘブライ 6章11節は 宣教で
「勤勉さを示す」よう皆に勧めています
‘to show industriousness’ in our ministry.
The more you invest in
this form of ministry,
この宣教に時間を
費やせば費やすほど—
the more fulfillment you get
from the positive response of the drivers.
運転手の良い反応から
達成感を得られます
It is a good thing
to preach the good news at truck stops
トラックの駐車場で良いたよりを
伝えるのは素晴らしいことです
because all drivers need to feel God’s love,
運転手は皆 神の愛を感じ
神の気遣いを知る必要があるからです
to see that God really cares for us.
And like me,
they can make changes in their lives.
わたしのように 彼らも
生き方を変えることができます
エホバが将来の楽園を約束しておられ—
And they need to see that Jehovah
has promised a future paradise
それが自分と家族にどんな影響を
及ぼすかを理解する必要があります
and how this will affect them
and their families.
What great results
came from this preaching initiative,
素晴らしい結果をともなう
証言方法ですね
and what a delight to see
携わる皆さんが宣教で
ビデオを活用する姿を見るのも喜びです
how many of the publishers
used our videos while witnessing!
Although videos can be great tools,
ビデオは優れた道具ですが—
we all must continue
to develop our teaching skills
わたしたちは引き続きー
聖書から論じる技術を
磨いていく必要があります
and our ability to reason
from the Scriptures.
トラック駐車場で証言する兄弟たちは
まさにそうしてきました
The brothers witnessing
at truck stops did just that,
and the results
speak for themselves.
そして良い結果が生まれています
You will be happy to know that one
of the truck drivers who was interviewed
喜ばしいことに インタビューを受けた
イオン・ボルボティナは—
Ion Bolbotina from Romania
最近バプテスマを受けて
エホバの証人になりました
was recently baptized
as one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
宣教における わたしたちの努力を—
It is beautiful
to see how our efforts
エホバが祝福してくださるのは
喜ばしいことです
in the ministry
are blessed by Jehovah.
Sister Margarita Königer has seen
マルガリータ･ケニガー姉妹は—
生涯にわたって王国の業の増加を
見てきました
the growth of the Kingdom work
all her life.
She has served
as a missionary since 1966,
1966年から
宣教者として奉仕していて—
and we met her in Hungary,
過去9年間は
ハンガリーで奉仕してきました
where she has now served
for about nine years.
ブタペストは美しい都市です
様々な国に囲まれていて
ここは人種のるつぼです
とても国際的です
ハンガリーの都市ですが
あらゆる場所の人が通っていきます
わたしは中国語の畑で
奉仕する宣教者でー
ここで9年になります
宣教者になって47年になります
最初の割り当ては
マダガスカルでした
良い研究を持っていました
とても良い人たちだったんです
マダガスカルに4年半いました
その後 禁令になったため
出て行く必要があり—
追い出されました
幾らか荷物を持っていけましたが—
もともと物はあまりありませんでした
その後 ケニアに遣わされます
3年後 またもや禁令になりました
それでベニンに来ました
知り合いに少し証言しました
しかし 彼らは当時 共産主義者に
なっていたため注意が必要でした
ある日 軍と警察がやって来ました
スローガンを叫ぶ若者もいました
“エ フズ！ダンダン！
エ フズ！ダンダン！”
“自由になる！
自由になる！”
とても興奮していました
ベテルは取り囲まれ出られません
わたしたちは悪人とされたんです
次の日 大柄な警察官が二人来ました
“来なさい トーゴに連れて行く”
その通りにしました
荷物はありません
トーゴにいくために出発しました
ずっと彼らに証言しました
一人が証言し
もう一人は祈っていたんです
エホバについてずっと話しました
それから森で止まり
こう言われます
“車から降りろ！”
エホバが正しい考えを与えてくださり
“降りません”と答えました
祈り そこに座ったまま
動きませんでした
彼らが話し合っている間
“もし彼らが来ても—”
“降りなくて済むようできることは
何でもしよう”と考えました
彼らが戻って来て
“よし では行こう”と言い—
そのまま出発しました
危なかったです
それはわたしの宣教者奉仕で
一番危険な時でした
2人の姉妹だけでしたからね
わたしたちはトーゴに
連れて行かれました
それから4週間ほど待ち
新しい割り当てを受けました
ブルキナファソです
23年間その国にいました
市場に行って買い物をしていると
皆わたしのこと知っていて—
“マダム・モアガ マダム・モアガ”と
呼んできます
モアガとは原住民 モシ人のことです
モシは部族の名前で
モシ族の人をモアガと言います
それでわたしはマダム・モアガです
彼らの言語を上手に話したからです
人々から学びました
それで安く買い物ができました
反応はとても良く
いつもバプテスマを受ける人がいました
一年で10人
少なくとも8人はいたと思います
とても小さな始まりでしたが
成長していきました
長年奉仕したあと
マラリアにかかったため—
ドイツに遣わされました
その後 ここハンガリーに遣わされ
来て9年になります
ブダペストには幾千人もの
中国人が住んでいます
中国人の店やレストラン
小さな飲食店で証言しています
とても友好的で 今では大勢が
わたしのことを知っているんです
わたしは中国語会衆が大好きです
彼らは他の中国人やエホバの証人に
会うためにも来ていて帰りたがりません
良い霊があります
わたしはエホバにとても感謝しています
ちょうど良い時にー
正しい生き方に飛び込むよう
助けてくださったからです
全時間奉仕は旅行—
エホバが導いてくださる
旅行のようです
ですから心配はいりません
エホバが責任を持ってくださるからです
わたしたちの責任は忠実であることです
何が生じているか
エホバはご存じで—
エホバがお許しになることは
大丈夫なんです
若い人には皆 同じようにすることを
願っています
とても満足いく生き方を
逃して欲しくないのです
エホバと共に働くことに
比べられるものは何もありません
ギレアデを卒業してから
50年の間に—
In the 50 years
since she graduated from Gilead,
Sister Königer has learned
seven languages
ケニガー姉妹は 七つの言語を学び
五つの国で奉仕ししてきました
and has served
in five different countries.
最近 姉妹は
新たな割り当てを受けました
And recently,
she received a new assignment
ドイツ ミュンヘンの
中国語の区域です
—the Chinese field
in Munich, Germany.
Daily reading
and meditating on God’s Word, the Bible,
姉妹は 神の言葉を毎日読み
黙想することによって—
has given her
the strength she needs
宣教者としての割り当てを
喜びのうちに続ける力を得てきました
to continue with joy
in her missionary assignment.
The same is important
if you’re young.
これは 若い皆さんにとっても重要です
Taking the time
to properly digest spiritual food,
霊的な食物を十分取り入れー
聖書通読の質を高めるなら—
by enhancing your Bible reading,
can teach you to make good decisions.
正しい決定を下すことができます
For example,
whom should you choose as friends?
たとえば どんな人を
友とすべきですか？
Pay special attention to this music video
“僕のいる場所”と題する
ミュージックビデオに注目しましょう
entitled Where I Belong,
最善の友を選ぶ助けになるでしょう
which will help you choose
the best friends possible.
Now everyone, it seems to me,
Knows just the place he wants to be.
さぁ どこに 根を張り
そう どこで 咲かせる？
I know what’s right; I know what’s wrong;
And, yes, I know where I belong.
答えは 分かってる
僕がいるべき場所
It feels so good, so good to know
Where I should be, where I should go
目を見て 分かり合う
胸の奥 引き出す
To find good friends and company
Who build me up and care for me.
本当の 仲間は
ここにしかいない
やわらかく
Yes, here in my heart
The feelings are strong.
咲きはじめる
Jehovah, it’s you
Who’ll help me get through
エホバから
愛そそがれ
僕のいる場所
And show me where I belong.
もう 今は 見えている
My heart is sure, it’s clear to me,
I’m standing where I want to be.
どこにいたいのか
I read God’s Word. I make it live.
It moves my heart. What can I give?
エホバの声 聞いて
心は燃えてく
And now I know; yes, now I see
Where real friends are; that’s where I’ll be.
さぁ 行こう
恐れずに
僕らは 独りじゃない
They’re all I want; they’re family;
Jehovah’s gift with love to me.
本当の友情は
愛の贈り物
Yes, here in my heart
The feelings are strong.
やわらかく
照らされる
エホバから
Jehovah, it’s you
Who’ll help me get through
光 受け
僕のいる場所
And show me where I belong.
What a fine young man!
素晴らしい若者ですね！
And he made the right decisions.
彼は正しい決定を下し—
He decided he belongs
in Jehovah’s organization.
エホバの組織に
自分のいる場所を見いだしました
And did you notice his habit?
どんな習慣を保っていましたか？
He read the Bible regularly,
聖書を定期的に読み
旅行にも携えていきました
brought it with him on the trip,
meditated about what he read
そして 通読の途中にも 宣教の間も
読んだことを黙想していました
—both after reading
and also when out in the ministry.
He took the time to grasp
the wonders of Jehovah’s creation,
さらに エホバの創造のみ業について
思い巡らす時間を取り分けました
and we need to do the same.
わたしたちもそうしましょう
We need to enhance our Bible reading
聖書通読の質を高めましょう
—visualize what we read
and try to get the whole picture.
読んだことを思いに描き
全体像をつかみましょう
And the organization
has given us many fine tools
聖書の記述を思いに描く点で
組織は素晴らしい道具を備えてきました
to visualize our Bible reading,
such as the illustrations
in our publications, audio dramas,
出版物の挿絵 音声劇
劇形式の聖書朗読 そしてビデオなどです
and dramatic Bible readings
and videos.
Make full use of them,
これらを十分に活用し
学んだことを黙想してください
and meditate about what you learn.
Thanks, Rocky,
I agree with everything you’ve said.
ロッキー わたしもまったく同感です
Well, as of September the 1st,
さて 9月1日以降—
members of the Bethel family
have been moving
ベテル家族はブルックリンから
ニューヨーク ウォーウィックのー
from Brooklyn to our new headquarters
at Warwick, New York.
新たな世界本部に移転します
Now, if you’re listening in from Britain,
that’s Warwick to you.
英国の皆さんにとっては
“ウォーイック”かもしれません
Warwick or Warwick, it’s the same place.
Tomato, tomato.
“ウォーウィック”
“ ウォーイック”—
“トマト” “トメイト”
どちらも同じです
And we’re very,
very happy about this move.
わたしたちはこの移転を
本当に喜んでいます
It’s a tremendous project
to move the entire Bethel family
ブルックリンからウォーウィックに
ベテル家族を移動させるのは—
from Brooklyn to Warwick,
and it’s going to take some time.
非常に大きなプロジェクトで
時間もかかるでしょう
So we know you’re anxious
to see the property in person,
新しい本部を実際に見てみたいと
思うかもしれませんが—
but we’re not going to be able
to get the property ready for tours
準備が整って
2017年4月3日 月曜日に—
until April 3, 2017, that’s a Monday.
見学が開始されるまで
お待ちください
I’m going to repeat that.
もう一度いいますね
We’re not going to be able
to open for tours
見学ができるのは
2017年4月3日からです
until Monday, April 3, 2017.
それまでの間にウォールキルや
パタソンを見学する機会があるなら—
Now, if you
happen to be touring Wallkill
or Patterson between now and then,
it’s going to be a mighty temptation
ウォーウィックまで来て
周囲の森に入って 木によじ登り—
for you to tiptoe
up to the property line in Warwick,
世界本部をちょっとでも見たいという
誘惑に駆られるかもしれません
perhaps put some twigs
and branches in your hat,
climb a tree,
and see what you can see.
それはやめましょう
Please, don’t do it.
皆さんをきちんとお迎えできるよう
一生懸命 準備しています
We’re working very hard
to get everything ready for you.
施設を見学できるようにするため
良く整えたいと思っています
We want everything to be just right
when the facility is open for tours.
興味深い取り決めとして オンラインで
見学を申し込めるようになります
And here’s another interesting thing:
You are going to be able
to go online
and schedule a tour.
会衆や支部と協力して 見学のための
取り決めが設けられていくでしょう
And so arrangements are being made
with the congregations and the branches
so that they’re going to be able
to do that.
慌てて駆け込まなくても大丈夫です
So you’ll be able to avoid the rush.
加えて “生命の起源に対する見方”に—
We also wanted to take the opportunity
to mention that two new interviews
二つのインタビューが加わり
視聴可能になったことをお知らせします
in the Viewpoints on the Origin of Life
video series
have now been posted.
4月に始まった このシリーズには—
You may remember this series
from the April program.
命が 偶然によってではなくー
It’s about scientists
who have concluded
設計の所産として
生じるようになったという—
that life did not come about
by chance, but by design.
結論に至った科学者たちが登場します
You will find these new interviews
“経験とインタビュー”の
セクションにある—
in the “Interviews and Experiences”
category,
“生命の起源に対する見方”の
見出しから視聴できます
under the “Origins of Life” heading.
We’d like to conclude
with these greetings
では 結びに ボリビア北東部の
ベニからの挨拶をお送りしましょう
from northeastern Bolivia,
in a region called Beni.
この地域では 人口426人に一人の
割合で伝道者がいます
This area has a publisher ratio
of 1 Witness to 426 people.
区域は 多くの川と
ジャングルからなっています
Their territory consists
mainly of rivers and jungles.
The approximately 350 publishers
リベラルタとグアヤラメリンには
350名ほどの伝道者がいて—
in the cities of Riberalta
and Guayaramerín
区域の隅々に達するため
創意工夫をしています
need to be innovative to reach
all corners of their territory.
例えば 支部の指導の下—
For example,
証人のパイロットの操縦する飛行機で
孤立した集落を訪問しています
under the direction of the local branch,
a Witness pilot
flies brothers to isolated populations.
また 川のほとりにある集落には
船でしか行くことができません
In other cases, some communities
located on the banks of rivers
are reachable
そのため 船による証言旅行が
時おり 計画されています
only by boat.
Thus, preaching trips by boat
are arranged from time to time.
旅行が 一か月以上に
及ぶこともあります
Some trips last well over a month.
But some parts of the territory
can be reached by motorcycle.
さらに バイクでしか行けない
区域もあります
The brothers and sisters travel
それらの区域を網羅するため—
兄弟姉妹が四時間かけて
移動することもあります
up to four hours
to cover such territories.
ベニの兄弟姉妹が
温かい愛を送っています
The brothers and sisters in Beni
send their warm love, and so do we,
わたしたちも 世界中の皆さんに
愛を送ります
to all of you around the world.
ロッキー プログラムの提供に
協力してくださりー
Rocky, I’d like to thank you for doing
the heavy lifting for me during this program.
ありがとうございました
本当に助けになりました
You’re a good brother,
you know that?
My privilege.
こちらこそ
He’s a good brother.
ニューヨーク市 ブルックリンから
JW Broadcasting でした!
And this is JW Broadcasting
in Brooklyn, New York.